Finding Aid for East Michigan Environmental Action Council Records 1969-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
East Michigan Environmental Action Council Records 1969-1989
East Michigan Environmental Action Council.
6 linear feet
Citizens action group concerned with health and environmental issues. Series in record group include Administrative, Grants and Proposals, Litigation, Topical, and Great Lakes and Water Resources Planning Commission.
90189 Bn 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by EMEAC (donor no. 7817 ) in June 1990.
The record group is open for research.
The East Michigan Environmental Action Council (EMEAC) was established in 1970 by a group of dedicated individuals who shared a concern for the health of people and the environment. They determined there was a need for an action-oriented group to address environmental problems directly affecting southeast Michigan. EMEAC was an outgrowth of the environmental grass-roots movement of the 1960s, and came into being in conjunction with the first Earth Day in 1970.
In 1969, the National Association of Junior Leagues announced a national conference on "Strategies for Environmental Control." Each local league was to send two representatives to the conference. Sara McGath and Dorothy Hoffman were chosen to represent the Junior League of Birmingham, Michigan. As a result of the national conference, the two delegates were inspired to create a local environmental protection council. With the support of the Junior League of Birmingham and under the direction of the League's Public Affairs Committee chaired by Susan Cooper, an umbrella organization was formed. This enabled the League to work directly with its own members as well as with members of other organizations. After two meetings of this new task force, the group had attracted fifteen members representing both individuals and organizations, including the League of Women Voters, The Association of American University Women, Planned Parenthood, a number of churches, and other environmentally concerned groups.
Seeking further guidance, the task force met with Shirley Meadowcroft, executive director of the West Michigan Environmental Action Council (WMEAC), to learn about the organization and functions of the Grand Rapids group. At that time, WMEAC was an established "umbrella" council representing some 700 individuals and 50 groups. Acting on the advice of WMEAC, in 1971 the Birmingham task force incorporated itself as EMEAC, a non-profit, tax-exempt organization. By the end of the year EMEAC counted 75 individuals and 27 organizations among its members.
After its incorporation, EMEAC mandated a three-fold mission encompassing community education, legislative action, and communication of environmental information. An office was established to handle community inquiries and house a library of environmental resource material. Community education was designed to educate the public about environmental problems and solutions. EMEAC has educational programs aimed at both children and adults, offering the screening of environmental films and the distribution of materials through schools and service organizations. Education is also carried out through the publication of brochures and the organizational newsletter Target: Earth. Legislative action includes lobbying for legislation that would encourage environmentally-sound progress, and the oversight of the administration and enforcement of laws that affect the environment. EMEAC follows both a pro-active and reactive policy toward environmental legislation. It works to strengthen and enforce legislation, and to provide information to legislators early in the deliberative process. Other activities include drafting proposed legislation and the preparation of rules and regulations for the enactment of environmental policies. In addition, among the most notable legislative issues EMEAC has been involved with are the Goemaere and Anderson Wetlands Protection Acts, and the Hazardous Waste and Solid Waste Management Acts. EMEAC has increasingly become involved in litigation to bolster and uphold environmental policy. The mission of communication is conducted in a variety of ways, ranging from establishing media contacts to providing testimony at public hearings. Members speak at public meetings arranged by EMEAC's speaker's bureau, which offers a number of informed and educated specialists. Staff members also serve as liaisons with other local environmental and governmental organizations such as Concern, Inc. and the Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG). In 1976, EMEAC consolidated with Environmental Action Now (EAN) and merged with the East Michigan Environmental Action Corporation. Under the 1976 Federal Tax Revision code, the new organization, which retained the name East Michigan Environmental Action Council, was incorporated as a tax-deductible corporation, and a new set of bylaws was written. The merger and consolidation allowed for the hiring of a full-time executive director, who greatly increased the visibility and impact of the organization throughout the state.
Funding for EMEAC is derived primarily from grants. The Ruth C. Mott and Joyce Foundations have been particularly helpful in providing grants and proposal funding. The Harder Endowment assisted the organization in fund raising during the years 1985-1989, when it supplied up to $200,000 to match donations collected from memberships. Currently EMEAC has 1200 individual and organizational memberships.
EMEAC's active membership is supplemented by six full-and part-time professional staff members. EMEAC's governing body takes the form of a Board of Directors and a Board of Advisors. The Board of Directors is responsible for determining policy objectives and goals. Members are elected at the annual meeting in May, and serve for a two-year period. The Board of Directors meets monthly with the exception of the summer months. The meetings are chaired by the president, who acts as the liaison between the boards and the office staff. Issues are drawn primarily from the Board's three major task forces: water resources protection, toxic substance management, and farmland preservation. The Board of Directors consults with the Board of Advisors, although the latter is not directly involved in setting policy. The Board of Advisors is designated as a committee of informed and environmentally concerned individuals. The advisors are comprised of scientists, lawyers, doctors and other specialists who act as consultants and resource people for the organization. Both boards are comprised entirely of volunteers. The professional staff members, managed by the executive director, implement policies set by the Board of Directors.
The records of the East Michigan Environmental Action Council (EMEAC) comprise 8 linear feet of materials spanning the years 1969-1989. The records have been retained in the order maintained by the organization and consist of 5 series: Administrative, Grants and Proposals, Litigation, Topical, and Great Lakes and Water Resources Planning Commission. The collection documents the founding of EMEAC, its development and operation as an important grass-roots organization, as well as a variety of environmental issues affecting southeast Michigan.
Subjects:
Citizens' associations--Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Michigan. Great Lakes and Water Resources Planning Commission.; Hazardous wastes--Michigan.; Refuse and refuse disposal.; Water.
- Administrative 1969-1987
  Administrative series (1 linear foot) includes annual reports, board minutes, materials related to the organization's history, and copies of the newsletter Target: Earth. Annual reports span from 1970 to 1989, although those for the 1980s are incomplete. Reports range from one to four pages, and summarize the council's activities, provide some budgetary information, and describe legislation that was either supported or opposed. Minutes are from the Board of Directors meetings, and range from 1969 to 1984. The minutes from 1969 are from the Junior League of Birmingham, Michigan, and document the first steps taken to form EMEAC. Later minutes record administrative activity, provide budget statements, and include reports from sub-committees regarding issues to focus on with recommendations for future action. Council histories are brief, primarily covering its founding and first few years. Several of these histories have appeared in Target: Earth, the official publication of EMEAC. The newsletter provides pertinent environmental news and includes announcements of upcoming events. It also provides legislative updates and editorial statements. The run of newsletters in this collection is sporadic for the early years, with several volumes missing entirely. It is, however, complete for the years 1985-1987.
  - Annual Meeting 1987 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1971-1981 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes 1969-1984 (Box 1)
  - Educational Program (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Newsletter questionnaires and reports (Box 1)
- Grants and Proposals
  Grants and Proposals (1 linear foot) contains reports and proposals submitted for grant funding. Most reports include summaries of the proposed activity. Activities include creating and publishing environmental guidebooks, and arranging workshops. Budgetary breakdowns are usually included in the request, and detail the variety of uses for the funding. A variety of agencies are represented, including local foundations and organizations and the National Science Foundation. The bulk of the materials relates to the Ruth C. Mott and Joyce Foundations, two of the major supporters of EMEAC.
  - Agencies
    - American Lung Association (Box 1)
    - Angell Foundation (Box 1)
    - Clean Michigan Fund (Box 1)
    - Joyce Foundation, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Junior League of Birmingham (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, Elizabeth Fund (Box 1)
    - MEC Proposals (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mott Foundation (Box 1)
    - Needmor Fund (Box 1)
    - Slocum Foundation (Box 1)
  - Projects and Programs
    - Acid Rain Education Programs (Box 1)
    - Chemophobia Conference (Box 1)
    - Citizen Empowerment/ Environmental Advocacy (Box 1)
    - Citizen Water Quality Education Program for Ohio and Michigan (Box 1)
    - Consultation Services (Box 1)
    - East Livingston Groundwater Protection Workshop (Box 1)
    - Energy Brochure (Box 1)
    - Farmlands Protection Educational Campaign (Box 1)
    - Formulation of An Inter-County Environment Center, A Proposal for Planning and Implementation Funds (Box 1)
    - Funding Requests Brochure (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Diversion (Box 2)
    - Groundwater Citizen Education Program (Box 2)
    - Groundwater Gertie (Box 2)
    - Groundwater Handbook (Ruth Mott Fund) (Box 2)
    - Guidebook Proposal: Hazardous Waste Facilities: A Guide to Local Community Involvement (Box 2)
    - Hazardous Materials Management Education for the Media (Box 2)
    - Household Hazardous Waste Disposal Project (Box 2)
    - Joyce Foundation Citizen Groundwater Alert Network (Box 2)
    - Kids Can (Box 2)
    - Oil Recycling (Box 2)
    - Toxic Substance Educational Campaign for Detroit and Wayne County (Else Kolhede Memorial Foundation) (Box 2)
    - Urban Action A Grass-roots Effort to Support Government Initiatives (NSF Proposal) (Box 2)
    - West Oakland Groundwater Leadership Team (Box 2)
- Litigation
  Litigation (1 linear foot) consists of court papers, legal documents, and reference files pertaining to several lawsuits filed by or involving EMEAC. The materials reveal EMEAC's attempts to defend established statutes against government and industry attempts to undermine environmental protection. Several lawsuits were filed against developers intruding on environmental preserves. Notable cases include the effort to prevent the operation of the Detroit Municipal Incinerator, designed to burn trash to create energy, and the attempts of American Aggregates to re-zone residential property in Highland Township to allow gravel mining. These cases are well documented, illustrating the environmental impact argued by EMEAC and others.
  - American Aggregates, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Cascade Resource Recovery, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Detroit Incinerator, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Hammond vs. Tanner (Box 2)
  - Edward C. Levy Gravel Operations, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Local Enabling Legislation (Box 2)
  - S.B. McLaughlin Associates, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Phosphate Bans (Lake Eutrophication) (Box 3)
  - Phosphate Litigation (Box 3)
  - Wetlands Cases (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  Topical Files (3 linear feet) consists of basic reference files created by EMEAC staff members. These files include articles, summaries, correspondence and legislative histories. The arrangement of these topical files retains the hierarchy employed by EMEAC. The arrangement is alphabetical, first by broad subject headings, and then alphabetically by topic under each subject heading. Folders include both general background informational files as well as files on specific topics such as hazardous waste rules, and zoning rules and legislation.
  - Air Pollution
    - Consumer's Power (Cobb-Campell Power Plants) (Box 3)
    - Detroit Edison (Box 3)
    - Dow Chemical (Box 3)
    - Great Lakes Steel (Box 3)
    - State Implementation Plan (Box 3)
    - Wayne County Air Pollution Control Division (Box 3)
  - Air Pollutants
    - Freon (Box 3)
    - Lead (Box 3)
    - Mobile Source Issue (Box 3)
  - Defense
    - Project ELF (Extremely Low Frequency radiation) (Seafarer/ Sanguine) (Box 3)
  - Energy
    - General (Box 3)
    - Conservation (Box 3)
    - Education (Box 3)
    - Energy Mobilization Board (Box 3)
    - Michigan Energy Policy (Box 3)
    - Nuclear Fission (Box 3)
    - Nuclear Power (Box 3)
    - Synthetic Fuel (Box 3)
    - World Energy Conference (Box 3)
  - Economics
    - Agri-Business (Box 3)
    - Environment and Jobs (Box 3)
    - Environmental Impairment and Liability Insurance (Box 3)
    - Environmental Response Act (Box 3)
    - Farming (Box 3)
    - Farmland Retention (Box 3)
  - Great Lakes
    see also Box 6 Great Lakes Water and Resources Planning Commission
    - Beadle Bay Development (Box 3)
    - Great Lakes Water Quality Agreement (Box 3)
    - Great Lakes Water Resources Conference (Box 3)
  - Hazardous Waste Management
    - General (Box 3)
    - Governor's Strategy for Hazardous Waste Management (Box 3)
    - Hazardous Waste Facilities (Box 3)
    - Hazardous Waste Management Committee (Box 3)
    - Hazardous Waste Rules (Box 3)
    - Hazardous Waste Siting (Box 3)
    - Household Hazardous Waste (Box 3)
    - Stablex Plant (Groveland Township) (Box 3)
    - Toxic Waste Site Interviews (Box 3)
    - Underground Storage of Gasoline, Study (Box 3)
  - Health
    - DNA Technology, Regulation of Recombinant (Box 4)
    - "Right to Know" (Box 4)
  - Lands
    - Forests (Box 4)
    - Kammer Trust Fund (Recreational Lands) (Box 4)
    - Land Use (Box 4)
    - Local Issues (Box 4)
    - Managed Growth (Box 4)
    - Non-consumptive Users (Box 4)
    - Off-Road Vehicles (Box 4)
    - Park LaSalle (Box 4)
    - Public Lands, Sale of (Box 4)
    - State Legislation (Box 4)
    - Urban Sprawl (Box 4)
    - Insurance Redlining (Box 4)
  - Mining
    - Dingman Bog Peat Mining (Box 4)
    - Hydrocarbon Management (Box 4)
    - Mineral Leasing (Box 4)
    - Reserve Mining (Box 4)
    - Sand Mining (Box 4)
    - Strip Mining (Box 4)
  - Pesticides
    - General (Box 4)
  - Population
    - General (Box 4)
  - Railroads
    - General (Box 4)
  - Resource Recovery
    - Legislation (Box 4)
    - Returnable Beverage Containers (Box 4)
  - Solid Waste Management
    - General (Box 4)
    - Holly Township Site (Box 4)
    - Ingham County/ Herrgath Landfill Expansion (Box 4)
    - Kettlewell Landfill (Gratiot Township) (Box 4)
    - Local Solid Waste Public Participation Project (Box 4)
    - Macomb County Solid Waste Management Plan (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Sites (Box 4)
    - Oakland County Solid Waste Plan (Box 4)
    - Solid Waste Management Act (Box 4)
  - Transportation
    - M-59 Highway (Box 4)
    - Michigan Transportation System (Box 4)
    - Northwestern Highway, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Public Transportation (Box 4)
    - Roadside Herbicides (Box 4)
  - Water
    - Clean Water Act: Overview (Box 4)
    - Clinton River Hydro-study (Box 4)
    - Dams (Box 4)
    - Dead Stream Impoundment (Box 4)
    - Detroit Water Treatment (Box 4)
    - Drains (Box 4)
    - Drain Code Recodification (Box 5)
    - Drinking Water (Box 5)
    - Facility Plan (Box 5)
    - Flood Plans (Box 5)
    - Groundwater Contamination (Box 5)
    - Huron River (Box 5)
    - Huron Valley Hospital, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Hydrological Investigation of a Proposed Waterway Disposal Sight (Box 5)
    - Inland Lakes and Streams, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Michigan Environmental Review Board (Box 5)
    - Natural Rivers Program (Box 5)
    - National Pollution Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) (Box 5)
    - Non-Point Pollution (Box 5)
    - Oil Spills (Box 5)
    - Pernick-Peterson Drain Plan (Box 5)
    - Phosphates (Box 5)
    - Red Run/ Lower Clinton River Flood Control Project (Box 5)
    - Right to Water (Box 5)
    - Septic Systems Maintenance (Box 5)
    - Sewers (Box 5)
    - Sludge (Box 5)
    - Storm Water, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Storm Water Management Workshop (Box 5)
    - Tennessee-Tombigbee Waterway (Box 5)
    - Wastewater (Box 5)
    - Water Quality (Box 5)
    - Water Treatment, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Weather
    - Weather Modification (Box 5)
  - Wetlands
    - Local Agreements (Box 5)
    - Local Ordinances (Box 5)
    - MEC Wetlands Committee (Box 5)
    - Pentwater Marsh, "Spatial and Temporal Distribution and Abundance of Larval Fishes in Pentwater Marsh, A Coastal Wetland On Lake Michigan" (Box 5)
    - St. Johns Marsh (Box 5)
    - West Bloomfield Township Floodplains and Wetlands Protection Ordinance (Box 5)
    - Wetland Protection (Box 5)
    - Wetlands Inventory Preparatory Study of Michigan (Box 5)
    - Wetlands Training Bulletin (Box 5)
  - Wild Life
    - Endangered Species (Box 5)
    - Falconry (Box 5)
    - Non-game Check Off (Box 5)
  - Winter Navigation
    - Congressional Hearings (Box 6)
    - Great Lakes (Box 6)
  - Zoning
    - Planning and Zoning (Box 6)
    - Zoning Rules and Legislation (Box 6)
- Great Lakes And Water Resources Planning Commission
  Great Lakes and Water Resources Planning Commission (1 linear foot) documents the activities and research of a specific committee on which an EMEAC board member served. The Great Lakes and Water Resources Planning Commission was a committee established in 1985 comprised of representatives of major interests throughout the state, including government, industry, and environmentalists. The commission focused primarily on issues of water pollution and water quality. The commission contained several subcommittees which focused on specific aspects of water pollution, toxic contamination in lakes and groundwater, and water quality standards. Materials consist of reports, legislative histories, and correspondence generated by commission members.
  - Buda, Steve (Engineer) Interview Questions (Box 6)
  - Clinton River Watershed Council (Box 6)
  - Competing Water Uses/ Water Rights (Committee B), 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Detroit City Council Proposed Wastewater Discharge Control Ordinance (Box 6)
  - Great Lakes Diversion, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Great Lakes Water Quantity and Water Quality Management (Committee H) (Box 6)
  - Groundwater Protection Management (Committee D), 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Groundwater Questionnaire Responses (Committee D) (Box 6)
  - Michigan Water Resources Commission Staff Report Rule 57 Package (Box 6)
  - National Pollution Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) (Box 6)
  - Permit Limitations, Glossary of Terms (Box 6)
  - Point/ Non-Point Source Pollution Issues (Committee C) (Box 6)
  - Proposed Surface Water Quality Standards Derivation Procedures for Chemical Substances (Advisory Committee) (Box 6)
  - Surface Water Protection (Pre-Treatment) (Box 6)
  - Surface Water Quality Standards Proposed Amendment to the Part 4 Rules (Box 6)
  - Toxic Contamination of Water Resources (Box 6)
  - Toxic Substances Water Quality Standards Development (Cost Benefit Analysis) (Box 6)
  - Water Planning and Management in Michigan, Assessment of Institutional Frameworks (Committee G) (Box 6)
  - Water Quality-Based Effluent Limitations for Chemicals (Box 6)
  - Water Quality Standards Act (Box 6)
  - Water Quality Standards Public Hearing Record (Box 6)
  - Water Quality Standards Revisions 1968-1977 (Box 6)
  - Water Resources Data Needs Committee (Committee E) (Box 6)
  - Water Resources for the Future: Michigan's Action Plan (Box 6)
  - Water Resources Management, Role of Local Government (Committee A) (Box 6)
  - Wetlands Management (Box 6)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library is the repository for other materials pertaining to environmental protection. The records of the West Michigan Environmental Action Council (WMEAC) are available for research as well as the personal papers of its members, including William M. Cary and Joan Wolfe. The papers of Helen W. Milliken, a civic leader and wife of governor William Milliken document a number of environmental protection issues. Records from the Michigan United Conservation Clubs (MUCC), a federation of public and private conservation agencies, contain information on the federation and its activities. Materials documenting the passage of the 1970 Michigan Environmental Protection Act are in the Joseph Sax collection.